Finding Aid for Construction Innovation Forum records, 1987-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Construction Innovation Forum records 1987-2006
Construction Innovation Forum.
7 linear feet
9934 Bw 2
International non-profit organization established in 1987 to recognize innovations in the construction industry that improve the quality, efficiency and cost effectiveness of construction. Administrative records, including minutes and reports; planning documents; nomination files for the NOVA Award; and visual material relating to award ceremonies.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials donated by the Construction Innovation Forum (Donor no. 8601 ) in June and July 1997. Additional records were received in 2002 and 2007.
The record group is open to research.
The Construction Innovation Forum (CIF), an international non-profit organization, was an outgrowth of the Construction Industry Cost Effectiveness (CICE) project, which published 23 reports from 1980-1983 on concentrated "problem areas" in the construction industry. The reports concluded that construction productivity in the United States had been in significant decline since 1965, resulting from the lack of innovation in the industry, manifested in outdated management techniques, inefficient labor practices, and conflicts among the industry's various segments.
The CIF was formed in 1987 by a group of primarily Michigan-based professionals representing various facets of the construction industry. Their purpose was to recognize and award innovations in industry productivity, cost reduction, and quality, through its annual NOVA Awards. The group is overseen by a Board of Directors, an Executive Committee, and other committees addressing various segments of the Forum, including membership drives, ticket sales to the annual Innovation Celebration awards banquet, and award nominations.
Since 1987, CIF has generated membership, endorsement, financial support, and general interest from all segments of the industry, including construction business owners, contractors, labor organizations, and educators. Its annual NOVA Awards attracts dozens of nominations from the U.S. and abroad, and the resulting Innovation Celebration has become a year-round selection and planning process. In addition to the NOVA Awards, CIF continues to promote innovation through its quarterly newsletter Innovator, which provides CIF members with forum updates and highlights of annual NOVA Award winners.
For further information, please consult the CIF web page, available at the following URL: www.cif.org.
The Construction Innovation Forum record group is comprised of 5 linear feet, including administrative materials and in-depth information about the various types of innovation CIF recognizes. The records are arranged into five series: Administration, Development, NOVA Awards, Visual Materials, Public Relations/Published Material, and miscellaneous Working Files. Together the records give insight about the state of, concerns about, and development in the construction industry at the end of the twentieth-century.
Subjects:
Construction Innovation Forum.; Building--Technological innovations--Awards.; Construction industry--Technological innovations.; Civil engineering--Technological innovations.
- Administration
  The Administration series comprises 0.3 linear feet and details the organizational structure of CIF. It includes records from the Board of Directors and Executive Committees (including meeting minutes, handouts, memos, and reports from various subcommittees) and some historical materials, including CIF's Articles of Incorporation. This series is arranged chronologically as originally ordered by CIF.
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors 1987-1996, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee 1988-1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - History (Box 1)
  - Executive director files
    - Meeting minutes and notes 1994-1997, 4 expandable folders (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes and notes 1998, 1 expandable folder (Box 2)
- Development
  The Development series comprises 0.2 linear feet and details the strategic planning and diverse involvement in CIF. Included are development plans and records of membership, endorsement, and fiscal sponsorship from various segments of the construction industry.
  - Major Sponsor Binder 1989 (Box 2)
  - Major Sponsor Binder 1991 (Box 2)
  - Membership 1990-1996 (Box 2)
  - Sponsorship/Funding (Box 2)
  - Strategic Planning circa 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - Support/Endorsement 1987-1991, 1996 (Box 2)
- NOVA Awards
  The NOVA Awards series comprises 3 linear feet and documents the process, planning, finalists, and winners of the annual award. The Administration subseries includes information about the awards process, "behind the scenes" planning materials for the NOVA Awards (including calls for nominations, press releases, awards show schedules, programs, and presentation scripts), and correspondence and informational materials about each year's winners. The Investigation Notebooks and Jury files are restricted for five years after their creation (currently restricted files have been moved to Box 5) and include miscellaneous jury records, score sheets, and investigation materials for NOVA finalists and winners from 2003 to 2006. These files in particular help show what CIF views as "innovation."
  - Administration
    - Process (Box 2)
    - Planning; 1989, 1991-1997, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Nominations/Winners
    - 1990 (Box 2)
      (see also Visual Materials, CDs)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992, 1 expandable folder; 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1994, 1 expandable folder; 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1995, 1 expandable folder; 1 folder (Box 2)
    - 1996, 1 expandable folder; 1 folder (Box 3)
    - 1997, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
    - 1998, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
      (see Visual Materials, CDs)
    - 2000 (Box 3)
    - 2001, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
    - 2002 (Box 3)
    - 2003 (Box 3)
    - 2004 (Box 3)
    - 2005 (Box 3)
    - 2006 (Box 3)
  - 1990 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Advanced Construction Technology (Box 4)
    - Face Floor Profile Numbering System (Box 4)
    - Microtunnelling Methods (Box 4)
    - Rogers Pass Tunnel Ventilation (Box 4)
    - U.S. Post Office Kit of Parts (Box 4)
  - 1991 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - BeKare Child Development (Box 4)
    - California Seismic Retrofitters (Box 4)
    - Infiltrator (Box 4)
    - Walkthru (Box 4)
  - 1992 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Bakerbilt Eurosteel (Box 4)
    - Ekofisk (Box 4)
    - Firestop Devices (Box 4)
    - Kyobashi Seiwa Building (Box 4)
    - Medo-Mesh (Box 4)
    - 100% Fall Prevention (Box 4)
    - Palisades SGRP (Box 4)
    - Shilstone Software (Box 4)
  - 1993 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Geopier (Box 4)
    - MecTool (Box 4)
    - Nova Containment Piping System (Box 4)
    - Self-Propelling Trench Shoring System (Box 4)
    - Strarch Clear Span Roofing Systems (Box 4)
  - 1994 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Air Admittance Valves (Box 4)
    - GraniteXpress (Box 4)
    - Jet Grouted Constructed Laminar Diaphragms (Box 4)
    - Osterberg Load Cell (Box 4)
    - Preston Folding Scaffold (Box 4)
    - Recycling Reclaimed Asphalt Pavement (Box 4)
    - Smart System (Box 4)
    - Soil Doctor Soil Stabilizer (Box 4)
  - 1995 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Hydro-Hog (Box 4)
    - Intralock (Box 4)
    - Odyssey (Box 4)
    - Paveset (Box 4)
    - Pipe Joint Tester (Box 4)
    - Tunnel Roof Casting (Box 4)
    - Ultrasonic Humidifier Retrofit (Box 4)
  - 1996 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Advanced Composite Construction System (Box 4)
    - Backflow Preventer with Failure Indicator (Box 4)
    - J-Up Construction System (Box 4)
    - Norcure Electrochemical Chloride Removal System (Box 4)
    - The "Paradigm" In-Place Concrete Recycling System (Box 4)
    - Project Equity Account Trust, P.E.A.T. (Box 4)
    - Recycled Plastice Pier (Box 4)
    - Spin Fin Pile Development (Box 4)
    - Ultra-Twist -- A325 Strength Blind Bolt (Box 4)
  - 1997 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 4)
    - Channel Bridge System (Box 4)
    - The Collom System "The World's Most Advanced Duct Cleaning System" (Box 4)
    - FiRP Reinforced Glulam Technology (Box 4)
    - National Center for Construction Education & Research (Box 4)
    - Silka Rapid-1, Hardening Accelerator Concrete Admixture (Box 4)
  - 2003 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 5)
    - Bridge Street Bridge Deployment Project (Box 5)
    - Chesapeake Bay Foundation Phillip Merrill Environmental Center (Box 5)
    - Close-Range Photogrammetric Methods for Structural Analysis (Box 5)
    - Launched Steel Girder Bridge Erection (U.S. Iowa River Bridge) (Box 5)
    - Lonworks Device Networking Platform (Box 5)
    - U-Tier Automatic Reber Tying Machine (Box 5)
  - 2004 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 5)
    - Concrete Maturity, Temperature Logging (Box 5)
    - Fume Free Hot Mix Asphalt (Box 5)
    - Micro-Composite Resteel (Box 5)
    - Object Genome Project (Box 5)
    - Personal Mobile Crane Simulator (Box 5)
    - Rouge Complex Sustainability Project (Box 5)
    - Tunnel Jacking for Boston Central Artery (Box 5)
  - 2005 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 5)
    - Asphalt Zipper Reclamation Attachments (Box 5)
    - Graphisoft Virtual Construction Solution (Box 5)
    - LeakfinderRT -- Pipeline Leak Noise Correlator (Box 5)
    - Prefabricated Reinforcing Steel Cage System (Box 5)
    - Soy Based Polyurethane Foam (Box 5)
    - Speed-Clip Rebar Tie (Box 5)
    - TITAN Bridge Lift System (Box 5)
    - WetSep -- Wastewater Filtration System (Box 5)
  - 2006 Investigation
    - Jury/Investigation (Box 5)
    - AquaBlok Composite Particle Technology (Box 5)
    - Asphalt Pavement Radar Analysis (Box 5)
    - FastFusion Poly Pipe Field Fusion Welding (Box 5)
    - GRIDFORM -- Prefabricated FRP Panel for Rapid Bridge Deck Construction (Box 5)
    - Lightning Switch (Wireless Electric Switch Controls) (Box 5)
    - Site Characterization and Analysis Penetrometer System (SCAPS) (Box 5)
    - SlipStone Extruded Wall Pattern System (Box 5)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series comprises 0.2 linear feet. It includes photographs from the 1989-1993 NOVA Awards banquets, two public relations VHS videotapes about CIF and the NOVA Awards, one VHS videotape of the 1995 Innovation Celebration program, and color slides from the 1993 awards presentation. Not all slides from the presentation are included; some PowerPoint slides and charts were removed from the record group before it was accessioned by the Bentley Historical Library. Also included is a CD-R74 (650MB) with a 1997 NOVA PowerPoint presentation and the March 1997 version of the CIF web site. (This CD was unreadable at the time the collection was processed.)
  - CD
    - 1997 NOVA PowerPoint and March 1997 CIF Web Site (Box 5)
    - Nominations 1990-2006 and Reports, 1993-1997, 2004-2006 (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - 1989 Innovation Celebration (Box 5)
    - 1990 Innovation Celebration (Box 5)
    - 1991 Innovation Celebration (Box 5)
    - 1992 Innovation Celebration (Box 5)
    - 1993 Innovation Celebration (Box 5)
  - Slides
    - 1990 Construction Innovation Forum and NOVA Awards (Box 5)
  - Videotapes
    - 1990 Construction Innovation Forum and NOVA Awards (VHS) (Box 5)
    - 1993 NOVA Awards (VHS) (Box 5)
    - 1995 Innovation Celebration program (VHS) (Box 5)
- Public Relations/Published material
  The Public Relations/Published material series comprises 1 linear feet. It includes CIF press releases, articles published and presentations given by CIF members about the construction industry, and print materials published by CIF, including several issues of their Innovator newsletter and a catalog of NOVA Award winners. This series presents CIF's major concerns about the construction industry, reports on innovative progress, and the Forum's promotion of innovation.
  - Articles 1988-1996 (Box 6)
  - Press Releases 1989-1998, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Print Materials 1991-1997 (Box 6)
  - Innovator, 1989-1997 (Box 6)
  - Programs/invitations (Box 6)
  - Talks 1987, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Publicity 1989-1997, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Winners press announcements 1990-1995, 1997, 7 folders (Box 6)
- Working Files
  - Board of directors miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Membership materials (Box 7)
  - Award miscellaneous (Box 7)